本格的[ほんかくてき]:genuine|full-scale|full-fledged, 夏[なつ]:summer, 夏[か]:Xia (dynasty of China; perhaps mythological), 日差し[ひざし]:sunlight/rays of the sun
本格的な夏の日差しが
肌[はだ, はだえ]:skin|body (in the context of intimate bodily contact)|surface|, 焦がす[こがす]:to burn/to scorch/to singe, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
肌を焦がしていく様に
恋焦がれる[こいこがれる]:to yearn for/to pine/to be deeply in love with
私もあなたに恋焦がれる
海[うみ, み]:sea/ocean/waters, ドライブ:drive/trip by car/driving, 運転[うんてん]:operation (of a machine, etc.)|driving|working (capital, etc.)
海へドライブ 運転するよ
横顔[よこがお]:face in profile/profile/face seen from the side, 撫でる[なでる]:to stroke/to caress|to comb (hair), 潮風[しおかぜ]:salty sea breeze/salt wind, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
横顔撫でる 潮風が気持ちいいsummer day
la la la summer day
ビーチパラソル:beach parasol/beach umbrella, カラフル:colorful/colourful
ビーチパラソルカラフルだ yeah
砂浜[すなはま]:sandy beach, 咲く[さく]:to bloom, 花[はな]:flower|cherry blossom|beauty||, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
砂浜に咲く　花みたい
KISS YOU あなたの心
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly, 感ずる[かんずる]:to feel/to sense
もっともっと近くにいたい　感じたい
私だけ見て
膨らむ[ふくらむ]:to expand/to swell (out)/to get big
KISS YOU ぐっと膨らんだ
胸[むね, むな]:chest|breasts|heart||, 思い[おもい]:thought|imagination|desire||, 唇[くちびる]:lips, のせる:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride/to give a lift, 伝える[つたえる]:to convey/to report/to transmit
胸の思い　唇にのせて　伝えたいと
だから　KISS YOU
だから　さあ　KISS YOU
Episode 5
Hachiken
Runs Off
You're getting pretty good.
結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
結構様になってきたよね
やっぱり:too/also|still
やっぱりそう思う？
Really? You think so?
筋肉痛[きんにくつう]:muscular pain/myalgia, なくなる:to die, なくなる:to be lost (e.g. luggage)/to be missing|to be used up
筋肉痛ももうなくなったでしょ
Your muscle aches went
away already, right?
まあねぇ
I guess.
I think I've gotten the hang
of riding Maro-Eyebrows here.
完璧[かんぺき, かんべき]:perfect/complete/flawless, 眉[まゆ, まみえ]:eyebrow/eyebrows, 乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||, こなす:to digest|to break down/to break to pieces, 気がする[きがする]:to have a certain mood or feeling/to have a hunch
もう完璧にマロ眉を乗りこなしてる気がするんだよなぁ
Hey!
You!
てめ！ そっちじゃないってーの…
That's not where—
Aw, he still doesn't respect you.
なめる:to lick|to taste, なめる:to be slippery/to be slimy|to behave charmingly
まだなめられてるな
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, マロン:chestnut, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
ちゃんとマロン号って呼んでやれよ
Call him Maron, his proper name.
そいつ:he/she|that, プライド:pride, 高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive
そいつ　プライド高いからさ
He's a proud one.
はい…
Okay.
The grass smells great.
草[くさ]:grass|ninja|not genuine|, 草[そう]:draft/rough copy|cursive script, 匂い[におい]:odour/odor|aura, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
草の匂いが気持ちいい
そろそろ:slowly/quietly|soon, 刈り入れ[かりいれ]:harvest
そろそろ刈り入れだな
It's almost harvest time.
Oh, look.
あれ
Th-That's a...
あれは…
ミステリー:mystery, サークル:group with a common interest (e.g. students)/club (e.g. company sports club)/circle
ミステリー…サークル？
A crop... circle?
Ooezo Agricultural High School Dormitory for Future Agriculture Managers
すげー:incredible/unbelievable
何かすげーもん見ちゃったな
That was quite something
I saw back there.
What's the matter?!
どうした！？
やっちまったよ
I've done it.
Notice
7/2/2013 (Sat)
Ooezo Agricultural High School  Guidance Department
We hereby notify the student below
of a violation of dormitory regulations/rules.
Class 1-C   Name: Beppu Tarou
Oh, a red slip.
赤紙[あかがみ]:draft papers/draught papers/callup notice
赤紙…
What's the matter?!
どうした！？
机[つくえ, つき]:desk, 赤紙[あかがみ]:draft papers/draught papers/callup notice
別府の机に赤紙が…
There's a red slip on Beppu's desk.
Ah...
もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something, 赤紙[あかがみ]:draft papers/draught papers/callup notice
もらっちまったか　赤紙
So you got the red slip,
also known as the love letter.
ラブレター:love-letter
またの名をラブレター
何やらかしたんだ？
What'd you do?
お菓子[おかし]:confections/sweets/candy, っ放し[っぱなし, っはなし]:keep ...-ing (negative nuance, with the state being improper, unpleasant, etc.)/have been ...-ing/leaving (something) on
お菓子　出しっ放しに…
I left snacks out...
Again?
またかよ
ホント:truth/reality/actuality, 食[しょく]:meal/(one's) diet|eclipse (solar, lunar, etc.), ルーズ:loose (e.g. belt)
ホント食いもんにルーズだよな
You're so loose when it comes to food...
回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||, 罰[ばち]:(divine) punishment/curse/retribution, 罰[ばつ]:punishment/penalty, 当番[とうばん]:being on duty
あと１回で罰当番になっちまうよ
One more and I'll get detention chores!
ミステリー:mystery, サークル:group with a common interest (e.g. students)/club (e.g. company sports club)/circle
ミステリーサークル！？
A crop circle?!
The unexplained phenomenon reported
primarily in England, but found worldwide,
イギリス:Great Britain/United Kingdom, 中心[ちゅうしん]:center/centre|-centered, 中心[なかご]:core|tang (of a sword, etc.)|middle of a nest of boxes, 世界中[せかいじゅう]:around the world/throughout the world, 報告[ほうこく]:report/information
イギリスを中心に世界中で報告される
穀物[こくもつ]:grain/cereal/corn, 円形[えんけい, まるがた]:round shape/circle|circular form, 複雑[ふくざつ]:complex/complicated/mixed (feelings), 幾何学[きかがく]:geometry, 模様[もよう]:pattern|state|conjecture of the current situation||, 倒す[たおす]:to throw down|to kill|to overthrow|, 倒す[こかす]:to knock down/to knock over
穀物が円形や複雑な幾何学模様に倒されるという
in which grains are flattened into
circles or complex geometric shapes?
原因[げんいん]:cause/origin/source, 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance
原因不明のあの？
嘘[うそ, ウソ]:lie|mistake|unwise move|
嘘ぉ
No way!
ホント:truth/reality/actuality
ホント　ホント
Yes way.
御影[ごえい, みえい]:image (esp. of a deity, buddha, royal, noble, etc.), 御影[みかげ]:divine spirit/spirit of the dead
なあ　御影
Right, Mikage?
うん
Yeah.
マジか
Seriously?
結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||, でかい:huge/big/gargantuan
結構でかくてさー
It was pretty big,
直径[ちょっけい]:diameter, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 円[えん]:yen/Japanese monetary unit|circle, 円[まる]:circle|entirety|money||
直径２０ｍくらいの円がこう…
a circle about 20 meters across—
収量[しゅうりょう]:yield/size of harvest, 減る[へる]:to decrease (in size or number)/to diminish/to abate, 困る[こまる]:to be troubled/to be worried/to be bothered
あれさー　収量減るから困るよねー
They're annoying because
they reduce the harvest.
余計[よけい]:too many|unnecessary|abundantly, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 増やす[ふやす]:to increase/to add to/to augment
だよね　余計な仕事増やすし
Yeah, they make more work for us, too!
腹立つ[はらだつ]:to get angry, ミステリー:mystery, サークル:group with a common interest (e.g. students)/club (e.g. company sports club)/circle
腹立つよな　ミステリーサークル
Crop circles make me angry.
農家[のうか]:farmer/farming family|farmhouse, 扱い[あつかい]:treatment/service
あぁ　農家にとってはそういう扱いなのね
Ah, so that's how farms
view crop circles...
It's me.
俺だ
I see.
ああ　うん　うん
Right.
Okay.
Oh?
ほぉ
情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, 間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman)
その情報に間違いないんだな
You're certain of this information?
Where?
場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
場所は？
Area 51, huh...
エリア:area
エリア５１か
エリア:area, まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
西川　エリア５１って　まさか
Area 51? Nishikawa, you don't mean...
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
そのまさかだ
That's right.
今夜[こんや]:this evening/tonight
あいつが今夜来る
It's coming tonight.
えっ！　本当か
Is it true?
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, 筋[すじ, スジ]:muscle|vein|fiber||, 筋[きん]:muscle, 信用[しんよう]:confidence/dependence/credit
確かな情報筋だ　信用していい
My source is certain of it.
You can trust the info.
It will appear tonight at nine.
今夜[こんや]:this evening/tonight, 現れる[あらわれる]:to appear/to come in sight|to be expressed (e.g. emotions)
今夜９時に現れるそうだ
ついに:finally/at last|in the end
ついにあいつが
Finally?
Nine, huh?
９時か
Yeah, finally!
今夜[こんや]:this evening/tonight
今夜　俺はあいつに会いに行くぜ
Tonight, I'm going to meet it!
Don't be ridiculous!
学習[がくしゅう]:study/learning/tutorial
バカな　９時といえば学習時間中じゃないか
It's still study hour at nine!
西川
Nishikawa...
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
お前　まさか…
Don't tell me you're...
Going AWOL?!
無断[むだん]:without permission/without notice, 外出[がいしゅつ, そとで]:going out/outing/leaving (one's home, office, etc.)
無断外出
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
やめなよ　西川
Don't do it, Nishikawa!
Yeah. The risk is too high!
リスク:risk, リスク:reduced instruction set computer/RISC, 高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by
そうよ　リスクが高過ぎる
Women and children,
stay out of my way!
女子供[おんなこども]:women and children, 引っ込む[ひっこむ]:to draw back|to be set back (e.g. from a road)|to withdraw (e.g. from the public eye)
女子供は引っ込んでな
俺は１人でもやるぜ
I'll do it alone if I have to!
ふざける:to joke/to jest|to make fun of
ふざけんなよ　俺も行くぜ
Don't be an idiot.
I'll go, too.
Me, too.
俺もだ
お前１人で行かせやしない
I won't let you go alone.
Now that I know, I can't pass this up.
話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., 黙る[だまる]:to be silent
話を聞いたからには黙っちゃいられないね
Guys...
お前ら…
I can't take responsibility
for what happens.
どうなっても知らねーぜ
Uh, but the punishment for sneaking out
is bathroom cleaning duty!
無断[むだん]:without permission/without notice, 外出[がいしゅつ, そとで]:going out/outing/leaving (one's home, office, etc.), 便所[べんじょ]:toilet/lavatory/rest room, 便所[びんしょ]:hairdresser's room in the residence of the shogun or a noble, 掃除[そうじ]:cleaning/sweeping/dusting
いや　無断外出は便所掃除だから
そうだな
You're right...
見せる[みせる]:to show/to display
八軒にこそ見せてやりたい
I want to show Hachiken most of all.
What're you guys talking about?!
いったい:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")/...in the world (e.g. "why in the world?")|one object, いったい:region/zone/whole place, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
いったい何の話だよ
I'll go, too.
私も行くわ
I want to see it, too.
私も見ておきたいの　あいつを
Are you insane?!
正気[しょうき]:sanity/consciousness/soberness, 正気[せいき]:true character/true heart/true spirit, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
正気か！？　駄目だ
No!
巻き込む[まきこむ]:to roll up/to enfold|to involve
女を巻き込むわけには…
I can't get women involved—
脱出[だっしゅつ]:escape/break-out|prolapse, 信頼関係[しんらいかんけい]:relationship of mutual trust/fiduciary relation, 大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect)
脱出には仲間の信頼関係が大事じゃなくって？
Isn't trust among comrades critical
for a successful escape?
Should a teacher get word of this...
情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 漏れる[もれる]:to leak out|to find expression|to leak out|
もしこの情報が先生に漏れたら…
Tamako, you...
貴様[きさま]:you/you bastard|you
多摩子　貴様
選択[せんたく]:selection/choice/option, 余地[よち]:place/room/margin
あなたに選択の余地はないわ
You don't have a choice.
Wait!
話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
待て　まだ　話は…
We're not done talking!
Stop!
止まる[とまる]:to stop (moving)|to stop (doing, working, being supplied)|to alight, 止まる[とどまる]:to remain/to abide|to be limited to
止まれ！
越す[こす]:to cross over (e.g. mountain)|to go over (e.g. with audience)|to pass time (e.g. a winter)||, 赤い[あかい]:red|Red (i.e. communist), 線[せん]:line|line (e.g. telephone line)|ray (e.g. X-ray)||
越すに越されぬ赤い線
The red line that must not be crossed.
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 越える[こえる]:to cross over/to cross|to exceed, 一線[いっせん]:line
男と女の間には越えちゃならねえ一線があるのさ
The line that separates
men and women...
Crap!
まずい:poor-quality/shoddy|unskillful, まずい:unappetising/unappetizing|unskillful, タイムリミット:time limit, 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 切る[きる]:to cut|to sever (connections, ties)|to turn off (e.g. the light)||
まずい　タイムリミットまで１時間半を切った
We only have an hour and a half.
作戦[さくせん]:tactics/strategy|military or naval operations, 会議[かいぎ]:meeting/conference/session, 開く[ひらく]:to open|to bloom|to open (for business, e.g. in the morning)||, 開く[あく]:to open (e.g. doors)|to open (e.g. business, etc.)|to be empty||
すぐに作戦会議を開く
War council, now!
風呂[ふろ]:bath|bathroom|room for drying lacquerware|, 諦める[あきらめる]:to give up/to abandon (hope, plans)/to resign oneself (to)
風呂は諦めろ
Give up bath time!
おーっ！
The boys' rooms have
iron bars on the windows,
男子[だんし]:youth/young man, 棟[とう]:large building/building with a long roof|counter for buildings, apartments, etc., 棟[むね]:ridge (of roof)|back of a sword|counter for buildings, apartments, etc., 各[かく]:each/every/all, 各[おのおの]:each|you (plural), 部屋[へや]:room|apartment|stable, 窓[まど]:window, 鉄柵[てっさく]:iron railing or fence, 設置[せっち]:establishment/institution|installation (of a machine or equipment)
男子棟は各部屋の窓に鉄柵が設置されている
まるで:quite/entirely|as if, 監獄[かんごく]:prison
まるで監獄
just like a prison!
Why not exit from the
main entrance, then?
いっそ:rather/sooner/preferably, 正面玄関[しょうめんげんかん]:front entrance/front door
いっそ正面玄関から出ては？
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
駄目だ
Negative.
宿直[しゅくちょく, とのい]:night watch/night guard/night shift, 目を盗む[めをぬすむ]:to do something behind someone's back/to do something stealthily, 職員室[しょくいんしつ]:staff room, 通過[つうか]:passage through (e.g. train skipping a station)/transit|passing (e.g. exam, bill through parliament), たとする:to appreciate/to be thankful
宿直の目を盗んで職員室前を通過できたとしても
Even if we manage to
get by the night watch
and pass by the
teachers' office,
玄関[げんかん]:entranceway/entry hall/vestibule, 重い[おもい]:heavy|heavy (feeling)|slow||, 二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 重[おも]:chief/main|main secondary or supporting role (in kyogen), 重[え]:-fold/-ply, 扉[とびら]:door/gate|title page, 開閉[かいへい]:opening and shutting, 音[おと, ね]:sound|note|fame|, バレる:to leak out (a secret)/to be exposed (a lie, improper behaviour, etc.) (behavior)
玄関は重い二重扉　開閉音ですぐバレる
the sound made by the
heavy double-doors
will give us away!
あぢ～！
Too hot!
This is stupid.
アホだ
何やってんだ？
What're you doing?
ちょっとな
Nothing really...
The emergency exit, then!
非常口[ひじょうぐち]:emergency exit
となると　非常口
Emergency Exit
どっち:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives), 選ぶ[えらぶ]:to choose/to select
どっちを選ぶ？
Which one should we choose?
南[みなみ]:south, 南[ナン]:south wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of south wind tiles, 逆[ぎゃく]:reverse|converse (of a hypothesis, etc.)|inverse (function), 逆[さか]:inverse/reverse, 方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action), 近い[ちかい]:near|close (in time)|close (relationship)||, 危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by
南は逆方向で公宅も近い　危険過ぎる
The south exit faces the wrong direction
and close to the employee housing.
It's too dangerous.
北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles
では北か
The north one, then?
場合[ばあい]:case/situation, 舎監[しゃかん]:dormitory dean, 室[しつ]:room|wife (of someone of high rank)|scabbard|, 室[むろ]:greenhouse/icehouse/cellar
その場合舎監室が…
The house master's room is that way.
House Master
Now that it's summer,
夏[なつ]:summer, 夏[か]:Xia (dynasty of China; perhaps mythological), 部屋[へや]:room|apartment|stable, エアコン:air-conditioner
今は夏　あの部屋にはエアコンがない
with no air conditioning in the room,
間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman), 開け放つ[あけはなつ]:to throw open/to leave open
間違いなくドアは開け放たれているはず
the door to that room must be wide open!
That's terrible!
丸見え[まるみえ]:full view/plain sight/completely visible
何てことだ　丸見えじゃないか
We'd be totally exposed!
ミッション:mission, インポッシブル:impossible
ミッション　インポッシブル
Mission impossible!
ホント:truth/reality/actuality, やる気[やるき]:willingness (e.g. to do something)/eagerness/motivation
あいつら　ホントにやる気かなぁ
Are they really going to do it?
But you kind of want
to see it, just once.
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree
でも　確かに一度は見てみたいよね
本当に行くの？
Are you really going?
バレる:to leak out (a secret)/to be exposed (a lie, improper behaviour, etc.) (behavior), 罰[ばち]:(divine) punishment/curse/retribution, 罰[ばつ]:punishment/penalty, 当番[とうばん]:being on duty
バレたら罰当番だよ
You'll get detention chores
if you're discovered.
Yes, tonight is my only chance.
今夜[こんや]:this evening/tonight
ええ　今夜しかないの
I must see it tonight.
今夜[こんや]:this evening/tonight, 手遅れ[ておくれ]:being (too) late|belated treatment, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
今夜見ておかなきゃ　手遅れになってしまう
Or it'll be too late...
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
八軒　一緒に入れといてやるよ
Hachiken, I'll put yours in, too.
Oh, thanks.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
ありがとう
うん
Tamako.
多摩子
うん？
What's the plan?
作戦[さくせん]:tactics/strategy|military or naval operations
作戦は？
南[みなみ]:south, 南[ナン]:south wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of south wind tiles, 階段[かいだん]:stairs/stairway/staircase, 踊り場[おどりば]:dance hall|landing (stairs)|leveling off (e.g. in the economy)
２０３５に南階段踊り場に来い
At 2035 hours, come to
the south stairs landing.
その後[そのあと, そのご]:after that/afterwards/thereafter, 南側[みなみがわ, なんそく]:south side, 非常口[ひじょうぐち]:emergency exit, 脱出[だっしゅつ]:escape/break-out|prolapse
その後　南側非常口から脱出する
We will escape from the
south emergency exit.
非常口[ひじょうぐち]:emergency exit, 北側[きたがわ, ほくそく]:north side/north bank
非常口は北側にもあるじゃない
There's an emergency exit
on the north side, too.
部屋[へや]:room|apartment|stable, 北側[きたがわ, ほくそく]:north side/north bank, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards
俺たちの部屋から北側に向かうには
To get to the northside
exit from our rooms,
開け放つ[あけはなつ]:to throw open/to leave open, 舎監[しゃかん]:dormitory dean, 室[しつ]:room|wife (of someone of high rank)|scabbard|, 室[むろ]:greenhouse/icehouse/cellar, 通る[とおる]:to go by|to run (between)|to go indoors||, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
開け放たれた舎監室前を通る必要がある
we'll have to pass by house master's
door while it's wide open.
かいくぐる:to slip through, 不可能[ふかのう]:impossible
その目をかいくぐるのは不可能
It will be impossible
to avoid detection!
よーし:alright/all right/right on
よーし　お前ら
All right, guys!
学習[がくしゅう]:study/learning/tutorial, 自室[じしつ]:one's own room, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
学習時間だ　自室に戻れ
Study time!
Return to your rooms!
しくじる:to fail/to blunder|to be dismissed
しくじった
I messed up!
What's wrong?
どうした？
携帯[けいたい, ケイタイ]:something carried (in the hand)/handheld|mobile telephone, 失う[うしなう]:to lose/to part with, 証拠[しょうこ]:evidence/proof, 写真[しゃしん]:photograph/photo|movie
携帯を失った今やつの証拠写真は…
Without my cell,
I can't take photos of it as proof...
携帯[けいたい, ケイタイ]:something carried (in the hand)/handheld|mobile telephone
携帯ならここに
I have a cell right here.
What?! That's mine!
携帯[けいたい, ケイタイ]:something carried (in the hand)/handheld|mobile telephone
えっ！？　俺の携帯！
ダミー:dummy, すり替える[すりかえる]:to switch (secretly)/to substitute/to sidestep (an issue)
ダミーとすり替えておいたのさ
I put in a decoy instead!
でかす:to do/to commit/to accomplish
おお　でかした
Oh, well done!
何で俺のなんだよ
Why mine?
ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation), 広野[こうや]:(a) plain, 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 宿直[しゅくちょく, とのい]:night watch/night guard/night shift
ったく　よりによって広野先生が宿直の日に
Damn it, it had to be when
Hirono-sensei has night watch, too.
しくじる:to fail/to blunder|to be dismissed
しくじった！
I messed up!
What's wrong?
どうした！？
学習[がくしゅう]:study/learning/tutorial, 宿直[しゅくちょく, とのい]:night watch/night guard/night shift, 見回り[みまわり]:patrolling
学習時間時は宿直の見回りが…
The night watch patrols the
dorm during study hour.
Hah, Hirono?
広野[こうや]:(a) plain
フッ　広野か
He's lazy. He just opens the
door and does roll call.
面倒くさい[めんどくさい, めんどうくさい]:bothersome/tiresome/bother to do
やつは面倒くさがりで
開ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 開ける[ひらける]:to become opened up|to develop|to be enlightened, 点呼[てんこ]:roll-call/muster, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
いつもドアを開けて点呼を取るだけ
Nishikawa, Hachiken,
Beppu: Are you there?
As long as you leave decoys and
someone to answer roll call...
代返[だいへん]:answer a roll call for another, 要員[よういん]:essential member/necessary person/personnel, ダミー:dummy, 残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save
代返要員と代返要員とダミーさえ残しておけば
Yes!
But that means someone has to stay behind.
残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
しかし　それなら１人残らねばな
じゃ　俺が…
I'll stay, the—
置く[おく]:to put|to leave (behind)|to establish (an organization, a facility, a position, etc.)||
八軒　西川　俺のことは置いていけ
Hachiken, Nishikawa, leave me behind.
Huh?
別府　お前
Beppu! You...
代返[だいへん]:answer a roll call for another, 任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||
代返は任せろ
You can count on me to
answer roll call.
残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
いや　だから俺が残る…
Um, I said I'll stay—
Don't tell me you're scared
of detention chores!
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 罰[ばち]:(divine) punishment/curse/retribution, 罰[ばつ]:punishment/penalty, 当番[とうばん]:being on duty, 恐れる[おそれる]:to fear/to be afraid of
お前　まさか　罰当番を恐れて…
違う　そんなんじゃねえ
No, that's not it!
I...
俺は…
体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, トイレ:toilet/restroom/bathroom, 窓[まど]:window, 抜ける[ぬける]:to come out|to fade|to wear a hole (e.g. clothes)||
俺の体じゃ　トイレの窓を抜けられないから
It's just that...
I wouldn't be able to get
through the bathroom window.
敵影[てきえい]:signs of the enemy
敵影なし　行くぞ
No enemies in sight!
Let's go!
余計[よけい]:too many|unnecessary|abundantly, 怪しい[あやしい]:suspicious/dubious|charming, じゃん:isn't it
余計怪しいじゃん
This just makes us look
more suspicious...
Are you ready?
覚悟[かくご]:resolution/resignation/readiness
覚悟はいいか
窓[まど]:window, いわば:so to speak/so to call it/as it were, いわば:rocky area/rockface/rock wall, ポイント:point, ノーリターン:no return (e.g. after buying something at an auction)
この窓はいわばポイント　オブ　ノーリターン
This window is basically
the point of no return!
強制[きょうせい]:obligation/coercion/compulsion
強制はしない
I won't force you.
残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left, 名乗り出る[なのりでる]:to introduce oneself/to announce oneself (e.g. as the person sought)/to come forward (e.g. as a witness, with a claim, etc.)
残りたい者は名乗り出ろ
Step forward if you wish to stay.
I won't stop you!
止める[とめる]:to stop|to park|to prevent||, 止める[やめる]:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel
俺は…止めない
Um, so why are we sneaking
out without permission—
無断[むだん]:without permission/without notice, 外出[がいしゅつ, そとで]:going out/outing/leaving (one's home, office, etc.)
いや　だから何のために無断外出するの…
Hachi!
ハチ
"A hero needs no reason
to draw his blade;
勇者[ゆうしゃ, ゆうじゃ]:hero/the brave/man of valour (valor), 剣を抜く[つるぎをぬく, けんをぬく]:to draw a sword, 理屈[りくつ]:theory/reason
勇者が剣を抜くに理屈はいらぬ
誇り[ほこり]:pride/boast, 戦う[たたかう]:to make war (on)|to compete (against)|to struggle (against adversities, etc.)
ただ誇りのために戦うのみ
he needs only to fight for his honor."
違うか
Am I wrong?
はあ！？
Huh?
強い[つよい]:strong/powerful|resistant, 強い[こわい]:tough/stiff|inflexible, 酒[さけ, ささ]:alcohol/sake, 杯[さかずき, さかづき]:sake cup/cup for alcoholic beverages, 杯[はい, はた]:sake cup|counter for cupfuls|counter for ships, octopuses and squid, 気分[きぶん]:feeling/mood
強めの酒を１杯やりたい気分だぜ
I feel like a strong drink.
よし　時間だ
All right, it's time!
許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
許せ　多摩子
Forgive me, Tamako.
It won't work!
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
駄目だ　ここまでか
Is this the end?
Why don't you go to the inner
courtyard from the bathroom?
トイレ:toilet/restroom/bathroom, 中庭[なかにわ]:courtyard/quadrangle/middle court
トイレから中庭に出たら？
Impossible!
中庭[なかにわ]:courtyard/quadrangle/middle court, 外部[がいぶ]:the outside|external, 接触[せっしょく]:touch/contact, 断つ[たつ]:to sever|to suppress|to abstain (from)
バカな　この中庭は外部への接触を断たれた
This courtyard's like a sealed room,
with no routes to the outside!
いわば:so to speak/so to call it/as it were, いわば:rocky area/rockface/rock wall, 密室[みっしつ]:room that cannot be entered (e.g. because it's locked from the inside)|secret room
いわば密室
No, what I mean is,
いや　だからさ
Boy's Bathroom
いったん:once|for a short time/briefly, いったん:one end/an end|part, 中庭[なかにわ]:courtyard/quadrangle/middle court, 舎監[しゃかん]:dormitory dean, 室[しつ]:room|wife (of someone of high rank)|scabbard|, 室[むろ]:greenhouse/icehouse/cellar, やり過ごす[やりすごす]:to let something (or somebody) go past|to do too much
いったん中庭に出て　舎監室をやり過ごして
use the courtyard to get past
the house master's room,
Inner Courtyard
House Master
Boy's Bathroom
トイレ:toilet/restroom/bathroom, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
こっちのトイレから戻れば…
then go back inside using
this other bathroom.
おお！
Then it's only 20 meters
to the emergency exit!
後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|, 非常口[ひじょうぐち]:emergency exit, 足る[たる]:to be sufficient/to be enough/to be worthy of
後は非常口まで２０ｍ足らず
Emergency Exit
でかす:to do/to commit/to accomplish
でかした　八軒
You've done it, Hachiken!
いやぁ…
No problem.
Huh?
あれ？
遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by
フン　遅い　遅過ぎるわ
They're late. Way too late.
I should've had them bring me a snack.
ついで:next/secondly/subsequently, ついで:opportunity/occasion, 夜食[やしょく]:supper/night meal/late-night snack, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
ついでに夜食買ってきてもらえばよかった
携帯[けいたい, ケイタイ]:something carried (in the hand)/handheld|mobile telephone, カメラ:camera, フラッシュ:flash, たける:to rage/to be fierce|to be excited, たける:to be boiled/to be cooked/to be done
携帯のカメラってフラッシュたけないよな
A cell phone camera doesn't
come with a flash, does it?
カメラ:camera
カメラ…
Camera...
しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
しまったぁぁ！
Crap!
"Keep your head down and get the hell over here."
"Someone's taking a crap inside. Keep quiet!"
What's the matter, Hachiken?
どうした？　八軒…
し～っ
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 間に合う[まにあう]:to be in time for|to serve (suit, meet) the purpose/to be good enough
早くしねえと間に合わないぞ
If we don't hurry up, we'll miss it.
Wait.
待て
うかつ:careless/stupid/thoughtless, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25)
うかつ　いつの間にあんなものを！？
Damn!
When'd they install that?
生徒[せいと]:pupil, 信用[しんよう]:confidence/dependence/credit
生徒を信用しとらんのか
Do they have no trust for students?!
Rotten teachers!
腐る[くさる]:to rot|to corrode|to become useless||, 教師[きょうし]:teacher (classroom), もめる:to disagree/to dispute/to fight (over)
腐った教師どもめ
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|, 南側[みなみがわ, なんそく]:south side, 非常口[ひじょうぐち]:emergency exit, 回る[めぐる]:to go around|to return|to surround|, 回る[まわる]:to turn|to visit several places|to function well|
駄目だ　南側非常口に回る時間はないぞ
It's no good...
We don't have time to get to
the southside emergency exit!
進退[しんたい]:movement/course of action/advance or retreat, 窮まる[きわまる]:to reach an extreme|extremely|to be stuck|
進退窮まったか
We've got nowhere else to turn...
やれやれだぜ
What a bother.
心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care
心配になって来てみれば
I came because I was worried.
Beppu?!
別府
所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 技[わざ, ぎ]:technique/art/skill, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
こんな所でこの技を使うことになろうとはな
Who would've thought I'd use this
technique here of all places?
What? That's...
な…それは！？
The ultimate technique of
Neapolitan pizza artisans!
ピッツァ:pizza, 職人[しょくにん]:worker/mechanic/artisan, 必殺[ひっさつ]:bringing certain death/deadly/knockout (blow), 技[わざ, ぎ]:technique/art/skill
ナポリピッツァ職人の必殺技
生地[きじ]:cloth|one's true character|unglazed pottery|, 生地[せいち]:birthplace, 回転[かいてん]:rotation (usu. around something)/revolution/turning, ことにより:by (means of)/by doing/due to, 遠心力[えんしんりょく]:centrifugal force
生地を回転させることにより遠心力で
By spinning the dough,
the centrifugal force makes the
縁[ゆかり]:related to (some person or place)/affinity/connection, 縁[えん, えにし]:fate|relationship (e.g. between two people)|family ties||, 厚い[あつい]:thick|kind|serious (of an illness)|, 中央[ちゅうおう]:centre/center|metropolis, 薄い[うすい]:thin|pale|watery||, 生地[きじ]:cloth|one's true character|unglazed pottery|, 生地[せいち]:birthplace
縁が厚く中央が薄い生地に
edge thicker and the center thinner!
Furthermore, by shortening
the dough's handling time,
触れる[ふれる]:to touch|to experience|to touch on a subject||, 短い[みじかい]:short, ことにより:by (means of)/by doing/due to
また　手が触れる時間を短くすることにより
the yeast remains intact!
イースト:east, 菌[きのこ, たけ]:mushroom, 菌[きん]:fungus|germ/bacterium, 壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.)
イースト菌を壊さない
When'd you master that technique?!
貴様[きさま]:you/you bastard|you, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 技[わざ, ぎ]:technique/art/skill
貴様　いつの間にその技を！？
会[え]:gathering (esp. Buddhist, festive, etc.), 会[かい]:meeting/assembly|association, こっそり:stealthily/secretly
ピザ会のときからこっそりとな
been learning it in secret
since the the pizza party!
Go, now!
行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|
今だ　行けー
別府
Beppu, how'd you get here?!
どうやってここまで来た？
舎監[しゃかん]:dormitory dean, 室[しつ]:room|wife (of someone of high rank)|scabbard|, 室[むろ]:greenhouse/icehouse/cellar
舎監室には誰もいなかったよ
There was no one in the
house master's room.
代返[だいへん]:answer a roll call for another
代返は？
What about roll call?
Ooezo Agricultural High School Dormitory for Future Agriculture Managers
部屋[へや]:room|apartment|stable, 消える[きえる]:to go out/to vanish/to disappear, 生徒[せいと]:pupil
部屋から消えた生徒
Students not in their rooms!
バレる:to leak out (a secret)/to be exposed (a lie, improper behaviour, etc.) (behavior)
バレた
We've been found!
Return immediately!
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, なさる:to do
今すぐ戻りなさい！
What?
何？　何？
Someone's running off?
脱走[だっそう]:desertion/escape
脱走したの？
本当にやった
They really did it...
多摩ちゃん？
Tama-chan?!
やられたわ
I was found!
Run! Flee into the woods!
走る[はしる]:to run|to travel (movement of vehicles)|to hurry to||, 森[もり]:forest|shrine grove, 逃げ込む[にげこむ]:to take refuge in/to succeed in running away
走れ　走れ　森へ逃げ込め
Nishikawa!
西川
Tamako!
多摩子
Use this to capture its true nature!
正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness
あいつの正体をこれで
気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|, 受け取る[うけとる]:to receive/to get|to take
お前の気持ち　受け取ったー！
I'll carry out your wish!
Come back! Hey!
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, なさる:to do
戻りなさい　こらー
夜食[やしょく]:supper/night meal/late-night snack, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
チッ　夜食あげちゃったわ
I gave them my snacks...
Oh, Beppu!
別府か
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|
他のやつらはどうした？　外か
Where are the others?
Outside?
追う[おう]:to chase|to follow (a set order, a trend, etc.)|to drive out||, 無駄[むだ]:futility/uselessness/pointlessness
追っても無駄ですぜ
Chasing them is futile...
They can run a furlong in 11 seconds.
足[あし]:foot|leg|gait||, 足[そく]:counter for pairs (of socks, shoes, etc.), ハロン:halon, 秒[びょう]:second (60th min), 台[だい]:stand|support|counter for machines, incl. vehicles||, 台[うてな]:tower|stand|calyx
やつらの足は１ハロン１１秒台だ
逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
お前は何で逃げないんだ？
Why aren't you running?
走る[はしる]:to run|to travel (movement of vehicles)|to hurry to||, 苦手[にがて]:poor (at)/weak (in)|dislike (of)
俺　走るの苦手なんすよ
I... am not particularly
fond of running.
あれ？　別府がいない
What?!
Beppu's not here!
Damn, he must've gotten caught!
捕まる[つかまる]:to be caught|to hold on to|to find (e.g. proof)|
くっそー　捕まっちまったのか
忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
やつのことは忘れろ
Forget him!
First, get through the woods...
ひとまず:for the present/once/in outline, 森[もり]:forest|shrine grove, 抜ける[ぬける]:to come out|to fade|to wear a hole (e.g. clothes)||
ひとまず森を抜けて…
Tokiwa?!
常盤？
What's the matter?
どうした？
Stay away!
来るな
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
こっち来ちゃ駄目だ
You mustn't come here!
A trap?!
わなか！？
Could they have foreseen our escape?
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 脱走[だっそう]:desertion/escape, 見抜く[みぬく]:to see through/to see the true nature of something
まさか　俺たちの脱走を見抜いて…
しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
まだわながあるかもしれん　戻るな
There may be more! Don't come back!
Sorry, Tokiwa...
常盤…すまん
Don't mind me.
気にする[きにする]:to mind (negative nuance)/to care about/to worry
気にすんな
Make sure to get a good look
at it, enough for both of us!
目に焼き付ける[めにやきつける]:to burn into one's memory/to sear an image
俺の分もあいつを目に焼き付けてきてくれ
Farewell, Tokiwa!
さらば:farewell|be that so/in that case
さらば　常盤！
Let's go, Hachi!
行くぞ　ハチ！
Hurry up!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
早く来い
さらば:farewell|be that so/in that case, 友[とも]:friend/companion/comrade
さらばだ　友よ
Farewell, comrade...
急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten, 間に合う[まにあう]:to be in time for|to serve (suit, meet) the purpose/to be good enough
急げ　間に合わんぞ
Hurry! We'll be too late!
たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however
そんなこと言ったって
But...
真っ暗[まっくら]:total darkness/pitch dark|bleak future, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
真っ暗で何も見えん
It's pitch black and
you can't see a thing.
It's the greenhouse.
ハウス:house
ハウスだ
時季[じき]:season/seasons, イチゴ:strawberry (esp. the garden strawberry, Fragaria x ananassa), 収穫[しゅうかく]:harvest/crop|fruits (of one's labors)
今時季はイチゴが収穫…
It's right around
strawberry harvest time.
しっ
Shh!
A bear?
熊[くま, クマ]:bear (any mammal of family Ursidae)
熊？
No...
いや…
Strawberry thief!
イチゴ:strawberry (esp. the garden strawberry, Fragaria x ananassa), 泥棒[どろぼう]:thief/burglar/robber
イチゴ泥棒
How dare you steal the
fruits of our hard labor?!
丹精[たんせい]:working earnestly/sincerity/diligence, 込める[こめる]:to load (a gun, etc.)|to put into (e.g. emotion, effort)|to include (e.g. tax in a sales price)|, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, 盗む[ぬすむ]:to steal, 度胸[どきょう]:courage/bravery/pluck
丹精込めて作ったもんを盗むたぁいい度胸だ
牛裂き[うしざき]:tying a person's limbs to two or four bulls and making them run in different directions (Warring States-era death penalty), 刑[けい]:penalty/sentence/punishment, してやる:to do for (someone)
牛裂きの刑にしてやる
I'll have you torn apart by bulls!
生ぬるい[なまぬるい]:lukewarm|half-hearted|lenient
いや　生ぬるいよ
That's going too easy on him!
刻む[きざむ]:to mince|to carve|to tick away (time)||, 堆肥[たいひ]:compost
刻んで堆肥に
Chop him up and make
him into fertilizer!
開拓[かいたく]:reclamation (e.g. wasteland)/cultivation|pioneering, 地[ち]:earth|place|territory||, 地[つち, つし]:earth|the earth (historically, esp. as opposed to the heavens)|low-quality torinoko-gami (containing mud)|, 年間[ねんかん]:years (period of), 強制[きょうせい]:obligation/coercion/compulsion, 労働[ろうどう]:manual labor/manual labour|Labour Party
開拓地で１００年間強制労働だろ
No, a hundred years of forced
labor in the frontier!
相川…？
Aikawa?
Damn, he had company!
しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
しまった　仲間だ
逃がす[にがす]:to set free/to let go|to miss (e.g. a chance)
逃がすかあぁぁ！
You're not getting away!
相川！
Aikawa!
Your death will not be in vain!
死[し]:death|death penalty (by strangulation or decapitation)|(an) out, 無駄[むだ]:futility/uselessness/pointlessness
お前の死は無駄にはしないぞ
We will press on thanks
to your sacrifice!
しかばね:corpse|kanji "corpse" radical, 越える[こえる]:to cross over/to cross|to exceed
俺たちはお前のしかばねを越えていく！
間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman), この先[このさき]:beyond this point/from now on/after this
間違いない　この先にあいつがいる
There's no mistake!
It lies ahead!
八軒　時間は？
Hachiken, what's the time?
えーと…あと１分で９時
Um, one minute till nine.
何！？
What?!
ヤベッ
Crap!
Is someone there?
誰かいるのか？
Come out!
なさる:to do
出てきなさい　さもないと…
Or I'll...
Komaba!
駒場[こまば]:pasture used for grazing horses (esp. ponies)
駒場
こんなこともあろうかと
I thought something like this might happen.
犬[いぬ, イヌ]:dog (Canis (lupus) familiaris)|snoop (i.e. a detective, a spy, etc.)|loser|
しかし　犬が…
But, the dogs...
Leave them to me.
任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||
任せろ
うせる:to disappear/to vanish, 犬[いぬ, イヌ]:dog (Canis (lupus) familiaris)|snoop (i.e. a detective, a spy, etc.)|loser|
うせな　犬チクショーども
Begone, filthy dogs!
取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
そ～れ　取ってこ～い
Here...
Fetch!
Hey, where are you guys going?!
こら　どこへ行く！？
I'll hold the line!
食い止める[くいとめる]:to check/to hold back/to stop
ここは俺が食い止める
But—
そんな…
Go! You have no time to lose!
行け　時間がない
Forgive us!
すまん
行くぞ　ハチ
Let's go, Hacchi.
ミステリー:mystery, サークル:group with a common interest (e.g. students)/club (e.g. company sports club)/circle
ここはミステリーサークルがあった…
This is where we saw the crop circle...
Yes, this is Area 51.
エリア:area
そう　ここがエリア５１
２人だけになっちまったな
We're down to just the two of us.
What time is it?
何時[いつ]:when/how soon, 何時[なんじ, なんどき]:what time?
何時だ？
９時８分
9:08.
遅れる[おくれる]:to be late/to be delayed/to fall behind schedule
遅れちまったか
Damn, we're late.
来た　来た　来たー！
Here it comes!
What?!
何だ　これえぇぇ！？
What is that thing?!
Who are you people?
何だ？　君たちは
What?
You can't be here.
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places
駄目だよ　こんな所にいちゃ
You'll get run over.
ひき殺す[ひきころす]:to kill by running over
ひき殺されちゃうよ
のいて　のいて
Move, move.
Sorry.
すんませ～ん
What, are those Ezonoo students?
生[き]:pure/undiluted/raw, 生[なま]:raw|natural|unprotected (i.e. not wearing a condom)||
何？　エゾノー生？
Huh?
What?
巨大[きょだい]:huge/gigantic/enormous, 自走式[じそうしき]:self-propelled (type), ハーベスター:harvester
うっひょ～！　巨大自走式ハーベスター来た～！
Here comes the giant
self-propelled harvester!
総重量[そうじゅうりょう]:gross weight, 万[ばん]:many/all, 万[まん, よろず]:10,000|myriad|everything|
総重量１万３，１８０ｋｇ
Total weight of 13,180 kilos!
燃料[ねんりょう]:fuel, タンク:tank (of liquid), 容量[ようりょう]:capacity/volume|capacitance, リットル:litre
燃料タンク容量１，３５０リットル
Fuel capacity, 1,350 liters!
エンジン:engine, シリンダー:cylinder, 排気量[はいきりょう]:(engine) displacement, リットル:litre
エンジン１２シリンダー　排気量２４．２リットル
Twelve-cylinder engine
displacement, 24.2 liters!
Why's it operating at
this time of night?
何でこんな時間に！？
Why?
何でって
夜中[よなか]:middle of the night/dead of night, 夜中[やちゅう]:during the night/at night, 一般[いっぱん]:general/universal|ordinary, 道路[どうろ]:road/highway
夜中に一般道路使って
It uses public roads at night
to go from hay field to hay field.
牧草[ぼくそう]:pasture/grass, 地[ち]:earth|place|territory||, 地[つち, つし]:earth|the earth (historically, esp. as opposed to the heavens)|low-quality torinoko-gami (containing mud)|, 移動[いどう]:movement/transfer|mobile
牧草地から牧草地へ移動してるんだよ
今夜[こんや]:this evening/tonight, 遅れ[おくれ]:delay/lag/postponement, 気味[きみ, きび]:sensation/feeling|tendency, 気味[ぎみ]:-like/-looking/-looked, 邪魔[じゃま]:hindrance|to visit (somebody's home)|demon who hinders Buddhist training
今夜遅れ気味なんだから　邪魔すんなよ
We're running late tonight,
so don't slow us down.
What's the matter, Hachi?
どうした？　ハチ
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
帰るか
Let's head back.
Here!
ほれ
Thanks...
あんがと
By the way, weren't there choppers
flying around this afternoon?
そういや
昼間[ひるま, ちゅうかん]:daytime/during the day/time from sunrise until sunset, 飛ぶ[とぶ]:to fly/to soar|to jump
昼間ヘリ飛んでなかった？
近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly, 自衛隊[じえいたい]:self-defence force/self-defense force|Japan Self-Defence Force
ああ　この近くに自衛隊あるから
Yeah, there's a self-defense
force stationed nearby.
What about the dogs?
犬[いぬ, イヌ]:dog (Canis (lupus) familiaris)|snoop (i.e. a detective, a spy, etc.)|loser|
あの犬は？
To scare away bears, right?
熊[くま, クマ]:bear (any mammal of family Ursidae)
熊よけだろ
ことし:this year
ことし多いっていうし
There's a lot of 'em this year.
エリア:area
何でエリア５１なんだ？
Why "Area 51"?
畑[はたけ, はた]:field (for fruits, vegetables, etc.)|field (of specialization)|womb, 番目[ばんめ]:indicates position in a sequence|divisions of a kabuki performance
この畑５１番目だから
This farm plot's number 51.
And the crop circle?
ミステリー:mystery, サークル:group with a common interest (e.g. students)/club (e.g. company sports club)/circle
ミステリーサークル…
毎年[まいとし, まいねん]:every year/yearly/annually, 季節[きせつ]:season
毎年　この季節に
Apparently, guys from
the next school over
隣[となり]:neighbor (neighbour)/next to (esp. living next door to), 学校[がっこう]:school, いたずら:mischief/prank|pastime, いたずら:useless/vain/aimless, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
隣の学校のやつらがいたずらで作るらしいぞ
make one as a prank
every year around this time.
駒場[こまば]:pasture used for grazing horses (esp. ponies)
駒場
Komaba!
How was it?
どうだった？　やつは
噂[うわさ]:rumour/rumor/report, たがう:to differ/to be different|to run counter to, でかい:huge/big/gargantuan
ああ　噂にたがわぬでかさだったぜ
Yeah, it was a giant,
just like the rumors said.
ほれ
Here.
おう　やったな
Ah, good work.
Looks like you managed to see it.
出合う[であう]:to meet (by chance)|to meet (e.g. of rivers, highways, etc.)|to emerge and engage (an enemy), みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
出合えたみたいだね　やつと
Aikawa!
相川
What'd you do with the thief?
泥棒[どろぼう]:thief/burglar/robber
どうしたんだよ　泥棒
警察[けいさつ]:police|police officer|police station, 引き渡す[ひきわたす]:to deliver/to extradite/to stretch across
えっ？　警察に引き渡してきたよ
Huh? I turned him over to the police.
Oh, thanks.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
あっ　ありがとう
But how?
でも　どうやって？
Oh, I called the cops
with the thief's cell.
泥棒[どろぼう]:thief/burglar/robber, 携帯[けいたい, ケイタイ]:something carried (in the hand)/handheld|mobile telephone, 警察[けいさつ]:police|police officer|police station, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
泥棒の携帯で警察呼んだの
I wanted to see it, too.
僕も見たかったなぁ
チャンス:chance/opportunity
またチャンスはあるって
There'll be another chance!
夏[なつ]:summer, 夏[か]:Xia (dynasty of China; perhaps mythological), 大[おお]:big/large, 大[だい]:the large part of|big|approximate size||, 三角形[さんかくけい, さんかっけい]:triangle
おっ　夏の大三角形
Oh, the Summer Triangle!
夏休み[なつやすみ]:summer vacation/summer holiday
もうすぐ夏休みだね
It's almost summer vacation.
These three months passed by so fast...
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, カ月[かげつ]:months (period of)
何か　あっという間の３カ月だったなぁ
The Following Students Are to Be Punished
with Bathroom Cleaning!!
Nishikawa Hajime
Hachiken Yuugo
Beppu Tarou
Tokiwa Keiji
Aikawa Shinnosuke
Komaba Ichirou
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), 便所[べんじょ]:toilet/lavatory/rest room, 便所[びんしょ]:hairdresser's room in the residence of the shogun or a noble, 掃除[そうじ]:cleaning/sweeping/dusting, 刑[けい]:penalty/sentence/punishment, 食らう[くらう]:to eat/to drink|to receive (e.g. a blow), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
あんなののために便所掃除の刑食らうなんて
I can't believe we got bathroom
cleaning duty for that thing...
"That thing"?!
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25)
「あんなの」とは何だよ
That harvester was awesome!
すげー:incredible/unbelievable, ハーベスター:harvester
すげーだろ！　あのハーベスター！
Sure it was,
すげー:incredible/unbelievable
すげーけどさ
but I was just dragged into the whole thing.
巻き込む[まきこむ]:to roll up/to enfold|to involve
何か　俺　巻き込まれただけじゃねえ？
イチゴ:strawberry (esp. the garden strawberry, Fragaria x ananassa), 泥棒[どろぼう]:thief/burglar/robber, 捕まえる[つかまえる]:to catch/to arrest/to seize
でも　イチゴ泥棒捕まえたから
But luckily, we caught a strawberry thief,
so we only got one day.
ラッキー:lucky, じゃん:isn't it
１日だけでラッキーじゃん
Hey, it's the bathroom cleaning gang!
トイレ:toilet/restroom/bathroom, 掃除[そうじ]:cleaning/sweeping/dusting, 組[くみ]:set (of items)|group (of people)|typesetting
あっ　トイレ掃除組だ
Idiots!
アホだね
寮[りょう]:hostel/dormitory|bureau (government department beneath a ministry under the ritsuryo system), 寮[つかさ]:office|chief|(Yaeyama Islands in Okinawa) person (usually a woman) whose duty it is to officiate at religions ceremonies, セキュリティー:security, 証明[しょうめい]:proof/verification/certification
この寮のセキュリティーはざるだということが証明された
We proved that this dorm's
security is like a sieve!
破れる[われる]:to break|to split|to be divided|, 破れる[やぶれる]:to get torn/to tear|to be broken off (of negotiations, etc.), 脱落[だつらく]:loss|omission|desertion|, 威張る[いばる, えばる]:to put on airs/to act big/to throw one's weight about
ケツ破れて脱落したくせに威張るな
Don't brag when you only dropped
out because your pants ripped!
Hey, so you saw it?
おお　あいつ　見たのかよ？
家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, じゃん:isn't it
でけえ！　家じゃん！
Wow, it's the size of a house!
I'd take bathroom cleaning duty to see that!
見せる[みせる]:to show/to display
俺にも見せろって
Let me see, too.
日本[にほん, にっぽん]:Japan, 台[だい]:stand|support|counter for machines, incl. vehicles||, 台[うてな]:tower|stand|calyx
日本に２台しかないんだってよ
There're only two of these in Japan.
The giants are the righteous!
巨大[きょだい]:huge/gigantic/enormous, 正義[せいぎ]:justice/right/righteousness
巨大は正義
後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|, 画像[がぞう]:image/picture/portrait
ハチ　後で画像くれよ
Hachi, gimme the pic later.
Okay, sure.
ああ　いいよ
八軒
Hachiken.
Yes?
はい
携帯[けいたい, ケイタイ]:something carried (in the hand)/handheld|mobile telephone, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
なぜこの時間に携帯を持っている？
Why do you have a cell
phone at this hour?
な…なあ　多摩子　お前はなぜ…
H-Hey, Tamako.
Why'd you—
下見[したみ]:preview|preparatory reading|siding (on a house)
下見したかったの
I wanted a preview.
下見[したみ]:preview|preparatory reading|siding (on a house)
下見？
Preview?
ハーベスター:harvester
あのハーベスター
Our farm's going to buy
that harvester next week.
来週[らいしゅう]:next week, 農場[のうじょう]:farm (agriculture), 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
来週　うちの農場で買うのよ
I wanted to see it with my own eyes
コストパフォーマンス:cost performance, 的[てき]:-like/typical, 的[まと]:mark/target
コストパフォーマンス的にどうなのか
実際[じっさい]:practicality|reality|bhutakoti (limit of reality)
実際に見ておきたかったの
to see what its cost
performance might be.
オプション:option/optional/selecting an option, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||, 万[ばん]:many/all, 万[まん, よろず]:10,000|myriad|everything|
オプション入れて６，０００万もするのよ
It costs 60 million yen
with all the options.
買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, 親[おや]:parent|dealer (in cards, mahjong, etc.)|founder|, 親[しん]:intimacy|close relative|pro- (e.g. pro-American, pro-Japanese, etc.)
し…しかし　買うかどうかは親が…
B-But aren't your parents
the ones who will decide...
父さん[とうさん]:father/dad/papa, 舞い上がる[まいあがる]:to soar/to fly high|to make merry
父さんたち舞い上がっちゃって
My dad's way too excited.
Men lose all reason when
gadgets are involved.
絡む[からむ]:to entangle|to pick a quarrel|to be involved with, 理性[りせい]:reason/reasoning power/(one's) sense, なくす:to lose something|to get rid of
メカが絡むと理性なくすじゃない？
ホント:truth/reality/actuality
ホント男ってバカね
They're such fools.
たまに:occasionally/once in a while, 手紙[てがみ]:letter, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
たまには手紙を書いてみようよ
ポストカード:postcard, でもある:to also be (formal, literary)/implies that as well as the earlier stated this is also the case|to be ... or something
どっかにポストカードでもあったけ
懐かしい[なつかしい]:dear/desired/missed, 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face
懐かしい顔に見けて
ほんの:mere/only/just, 数[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数[かず]:number/amount, 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|, ノスタルジー:nostalgia
ほんの数行ノスタルジーを
調子[ちょうし]:tune|vein|condition||
調子はどうですか
忙しい[いそがしい, せわしい]:busy/occupied|restless, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
忙しくしていますか
無我夢中[むがむちゅう]:being absorbed in/losing oneself in, 探しまわる[さがしまわる]:to search about for/to hunt around for/to look high and low for
無我夢中で探しまわってた
夢[ゆめ]:dream, 具合[ぐあい]:condition/state/manner, どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.)
あの夢の具合はどんなだい
気分転換[きぶんてんかん]:change of pace/change of mood/(mental) break (e.g. going for a walk), くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
気分転換くらいのノリで
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 歌う[うたう]:to sing|to sing (one's praises in a poem, etc.)/to compose a poem
一緒に歌わないか
無我夢中[むがむちゅう]:being absorbed in/losing oneself in, 探しまわる[さがしまわる]:to search about for/to hunt around for/to look high and low for
そして無我夢中で探しまわってた
夢[ゆめ]:dream, 続き[つづき]:sequel/continuation/(also suffix) continuation (in time and space), 語り合う[かたりあう]:to talk together
あの夢の続きを語り合おうよ
明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future, 頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
明日は頑張ろうぜ
未来[みらい]:the future (usually distant)|future tense|the world to come
今はそこにある未来へ
駆け出す[かけだす]:to run off/to break into a run/to start running
駆け出して さぁ 行こう
This story is a work of fiction.
The people and groups are fictitious, but the themes relating to food and life are firmly based in reality. Visiting the places and facilities used as models can be dangerous and may result it contracting diseases from the animals. Please enjoy this story as a work of fiction.